Postdoctoral Research Associate Phone: +1 (217) 417-7335 Research Laboratory of Electronics (RLE) Email: buyuheng@mit.edu

Massachusetts Institute of Technology Homepage: https://buyuheng.github.io/

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests lie in the intersection of *information theory* and *machine learning*. I have recently resorted to the tools from information theory to develop *theoretically justified* learning algorithms with applications to fair machine learning, model compression, and anomaly detection. More broadly, the primary goal of my research is to lay information-theoretic foundations for the learning algorithms with limited labeled data, including transfer learning and semi-supervised learning, particularly with fairness/privacy constraints.

EDUCATION

• Ph.D. in Electrical and Computer Engineering

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, USA Jan. 2017 - Aug. 2019

Advisor: Venugopal V. Veeravalli

Thesis: "Information-theoretic Bounds in Learning Algorithms"

• Master in Electrical and Computer Engineering

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, USA Aug. 2014 - Dec. 2016

Advisor: Venugopal V. Veeravalli

Thesis: "Estimation of KL Divergence: Optimal Minimax Rate"

• B.E. (with honors) in Electronic Engineering

Tsinghua University, Beijing, China Aug. 2010 - Jul. 2014

Ranking 7 among 240 students Double Major in **Economics**

Academic Appointments

• Postdoctoral Research Associate, **Massachusetts Institute of Technology** Sep. 2019 - present Advisor: Gregory W. Wornell

• Research Assistant, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign Aug. 2014 - Jan. 2019

Advisor: Venugopal V. Veeravalli

• UGVR (Undergraduate Visiting Research), Stanford University

Jun. 2013 - Sep. 2013

Only 18 students chosen from mainland China and Taiwan Advisor: Tsachy Weissman

Project: Time-series forecaster based on Online Aggregation

Research Projects

• Exact Characterization of Generalization Errors using Information Measures

Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Sep. 2020 - present

- Exact characterizations of generalization errors for Gibbs algorithms (randomized ERM) in both supervised/transfer learning settings using symmetrized KL information
- Information-theoretical framework that guides the selection of different transfer learning algorithms

• Fair selective classification/regression

Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Sep. 2019 - present

- Theoretical guarantees on using *sufficiency criterion* to mitigate disparities across groups
- Fair selective classification/regression algorithms by minimizing mutual information

• Information-theoretical Generalization bounds of Supervised Learning

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Jan. 2018 - Aug. 2019

- Tighter generalization error bound for supervised learning algorithm with mutual information
- Novel model compression algorithm that improves generalization performance by minimizing mutual information based upper bound

• Minimax Optimal Estimation of Information Measures

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Aug. 2015 - Jan. 2017

- Kullback-Leibler divergence estimation between large-alphabet distributions
- Minimax optimal estimator based on plug-in approach and polynomial approximation
- Superior performance in applications such as data-driven anomaly detection

• Data-Driven Outlying Sequence Detection

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

May 2014 - Jan. 2017

- Data-driven approaches for unstructured/structured outlying sequence detection
- Computationally efficient and (exponentially) consistent algorithms

PUBLICATIONS

Journal Papers

- [1] Y. Bu, W. Gao, S. Zou, V. V. Veeravalli. "Population Risk Improvement with Model Compression: An Information-Theoretic Approach," *Entropy 23*, no. 10, pp. 1255, Sept. 2021.
- [2] Y. Bu, S. Zou, V. V. Veeravalli. "Tightening Mutual Information Based Bounds on Generalization Error," *IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Information Theory*, vol. 1, no. 1, pp. 121-130, May 2020.
- [3] C. Wilson, Y. Bu, V. V. Veeravalli. "Adaptive Sequential Machine Learning," Sequential Analysis, 38(4), pp. 545-568, Jan. 2020.
- [4] Y. Bu, S. Zou, V. V. Veeravalli. "Linear-Complexity Exponentially-Consistent Tests for Universal Outlying Sequence Detection," *IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing*, vol. 67, no. 8, pp. 2115–2128, Apr. 2019.
- [5] Y. Bu*, S. Zou*, Y. Liang, V. V. Veeravalli. "Estimation of KL Divergence: Optimal Minimax Rate," (* equal contribution), *IEEE Transactions on Information Theory*, vol. 64, no. 4, pp. 2648-2674, Apr. 2018.

Preprints

- [1] Y. Bu*, G. Aminian*, L. Toni, M. R. D. Rodrigues, G. W. Wornell. "An Exact Characterization of the Generalization Error for the Gibbs Algorithm," (* equal contribution), submitted to *IEEE Transactions on Information Theory*, Nov. 2021, preliminary version appeared in NeurIPS 2021.
- [2] Y. Bu*, G. Aminian*, L. Toni, M. R. D. Rodrigues, G. W. Wornell. "Characterizing and Understanding the Generalization Error of Transfer Learning with Gibbs Algorithm," (* equal contribution), submitted to *International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS 2022)*, Oct. 2021, available at arXiv:2111.01635.
- [3] Abhin Shah*, Y. Bu*, J. K. Lee, P. Sattigeri, R. Panda, S. Das, G. W. Wornell. "Selective Regression under Fairness Criteria," (* equal contribution), submitted to *International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS 2022)*, Oct. 2021, available at arXiv:2110.15403.

[4] J. K. Lee*, Y. Bu*, P. Sattigeri, R. Panda, G. W. Wornell, L. Karlinsky, R. Feris. "A Maximal Correlation Approach to Imposing Fairness in Machine Learning," (* equal contribution), submitted to IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP 2022), Oct. 2021, available at arXiv:2012.15259.

[5] Y. Bu, J. Lu, V. V. Veeravalli. "Active and Adaptive Sequential Learning," available at arXiv:1805.11710.

Conference Papers

- [1] G. Aminian*, Y. Bu*, L. Toni, M. R. D. Rodrigues, G. W. Wornell. "An Exact Characterization of the Generalization Error for the Gibbs Algorithm," (* equal contribution), in *Proc. Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)*, Dec. 2021.
- [2] Y. Bu*, J. K. Lee*, D. Rajan, P. Sattigeri, R. Panda, S. Das, G. W. Wornell. "Fair Selective Classification via Sufficiency," (* equal contribution), in *Proc. International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)*, Jul. 2021. (Long talk, Top 3%)
- [3] G. Aminian*, Y. Bu*, L. Toni, M. R. D. Rodrigues, G. W. Wornell. "Characterizing the Generalization Error of Gibbs Algorithm with Symmetrized KL information," (* equal contribution), ICML Workshop on Information-Theoretic Methods for Rigorous, Responsible, and Reliable Machine Learning, 2021.
- [4] Y. Bu, T. Wang, G. W. Wornell. "SDP Methods for Sensitivity-Constrained Privacy Funnel and Information Bottleneck Problems," in *Proc. IEEE International Symposium on Information Theory* (ISIT), Melbourne, Australia, Jul. 2021.
- [5] Y. Bu, W. Gao, S. Zou, V. V. Veeravalli. "Information-theoretic Understanding of Population Risk Improvement with Model Compression," in *Proc. AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI)*, New York, Feb. 2020.
- [6] Y. Bu, K. Small. "Active Learning in Recommendation Systems with Multi-level User Preferences," AAAI Workshop on Interactive and Conversational Recommendation Systems (WICRS), New York, Feb. 2020.
- [7] Y. Bu, J. Lu, V. V. Veeravalli. "Active and Adaptive Sequential learning," in *Proc. IEEE Asilomar Conference on Signals, Systems, and Computers*, Pacific Grove, CA, Nov. 2019.
- [8] Y. Bu, S. Zou, V. V. Veeravalli. "Tightening Mutual Information Based Bounds on Generalization Error," in Proc. IEEE International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT), Paris, France, Jul. 2019.
- [9] Y. Bu, J. Lu, V. V. Veeravalli. "Model Change Detection with Application to Machine Learning," in Proc. IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), Brighton, UK, May 2019.
- [10] Y. Bu, S. Zou, V. V. Veeravalli, "Linear-Complexity Exponentially-Consistent Tests for Universal Outlying Sequence Detection," in *Proc. IEEE International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT)*, Aachen, Germany, Jun. 2017.
- [11] Y. Bu*, S. Zou*, Y. Liang, V. V. Veeravalli. "Estimation of KL Divergence Between Large-Alphabet Distributions," (* equal contribution), in *Proc. IEEE International Symposium on Information Theory (ISIT)*, Barcelona, Spain, Jul. 2016.
- [12] Y. Bu, S. Zou, Y. Liang, V. V. Veeravalli. "Universal Outlying Sequence Detection for Continuous Observations," in *Proc. IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP)*, Shanghai, China, Mar. 2016.

Professional Experiences

• Amazon.com Inc., Core machine learning group (Currently known as **Amazon AI Lab**) Title: Applied scientist intern Jun. 2017 - Dec. 2017

- Built a conversational agent that can actively learn users' interests to make recommendations.
- Conducted extensive research on customer purchase history with Yelp data.

TEACHING AND MENTORSHIP

• Mentoring graduate students:

Joshua Ka-Wing Lee, Ph.D. at MIT EECS, Tony T. Wang, MEng at MIT EECS, Gary Lee, Ph.D. candidate at MIT EECS, Abhin Shah, Ph.D. candidate at MIT EECS, Maohao Shen, Ph.D. candidate at MIT EECS, Fall 2019 - Summer 2021 Summer 2020 - Spring 2021 Summer 2020 - present Spring 2021 - present Fall 2021 - present

 \bullet Teaching and developing contents for MIT IDSS MicroMaster program:

6.86x Machine Learning with Python–From Linear Models to Deep Learning Fall 2019, MIT 14.310x Data Analysis for Social Scientists (live recitation and video recording) Spring 2020, MIT

• Teaching assistant:

ECE 365: Data Science and Engineering ECE 398: Making Sense of Big Data

Spring 2019, UIUC Fall 2018, UIUC

• Grader:

ECE 398: Making Sense of Big Data ECE 598: Computational Inference and Learning Spring 2017, UIUC Fall 2016, UIUC

Honors & Awards

• Outstanding Reviewer Award, NeurIPS

2021

• Yi-Min Wang and Pi-Yu Chung Research Award, UIUC

2019

• Nominee for Graduation Day at IEEE ITA Workshop

2019

• Student Travel Grant, IEEE ISIT

2016, 2017 2016

• Student Travel Grant, IEEE ICASSP

. . . .

• Outstanding graduate, Tsinghua University

2014

2012 and 2013

• Third prize, "Challenge Cup" the Tsinghua University

Student extra-curricular academic science and technology competitions

2012

• Second prize, Shing-Tung Yau secondary school mathematics competition

2009

SERVICE & PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

- Membership: IEEE, IEEE Information Theory Society, IEEE Signal Processing Society
- Reviewer:

Journals: IEEE Transactions on Information Theory (TIT), IEEE Journal on Selected Areas in Information Theory (JSAIT), IEEE Transactions on Signal Processing (TSP), IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI), Transactions on Information Forensics & Security (TIFS), IEEE Transactions on Vehicular Technology (TVT),

Conferences: NeurIPS, ICML, ICLR, AAAI, IJCAI, AISTATS, ISIT, ICASSP

• Vice President, Student Association for Science and Technology, EE Department, Tsinghua University

2012-2014